A Guide to the Children's Home Society of Virginia Records, 1902-2008
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Children's Home Society of Virginia Records, 1902-2008
The Library of Virginia
44227
16.6 cubic feet (33 boxes)
Children's Home Society of Virginia
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Portions of the collection are closed to the public for a set period of time, and can only be accessed with the prior permission of the Children's Home Society of Virginia. See notations in Contents List for details.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Children's Home Society of Virginia, 6 March 2009.
Biographical Information
The Children's Home Society of Virginia was organized in 1899, and chartered by the General Assembly on 30 January 1900. Inspired by the work of the National Children's Home Society, it was born of concern on the part of its founders for the plight of abandoned and neglected children. As stated in its charter, the Society's goal was "finding family homes for homeless, indigent, or dependent poor children in the State of Virginia, and other purposes incident thereto."
The Board of Directors selected John Garland Pollard (future governor of Virginia) as the Society's first president and the Reverend William J. Maybee as state superintendent. Maybee, who was to hold that position for nearly 30 years, articulated the ethos of the Society when he wrote in 1903 that "We are not to imagine that children of humble birth are therefore inferior, on the contrary the homeless child of the street is of the same clay as the petted darling of the wealthy...Both Christianity and civilization may be quite correctly measured by their treatment of childhood."
The Society received children in one of two ways, parental placement or court commitment. Representatives of the CHS traveled the state gathering children who were made wards of the Society and brought them back to Richmond. The children then underwent "a thorough system of renovation" that included the provision of "clean and comfortable garments," basic etiquette training, and examinations by medical and psychological doctors.
Initially, wards were placed under the care of Rev. Maybee's wife, Mary McLeod Maybee, and the Belle Bryan Day Nursery. In 1905, the Board purchased a house at 2605 East Franklin Street to serve as a receiving home and central office; another receiving home was opened in Roanoke in 1920. Local advisory boards around Virginia handled much of the recruitment and screening of foster families, and helped monitor foster placements. Those children who were never adopted remained the responsibility of the CHS until they reached adulthood, became self-supporting, or married.
Change came to the Society in 1926 when it joined the Child Welfare League of America and began a process of reorganization based on League observations. Their recommendations touched on a variety of areas including fire safety in the receiving homes, hygiene, nutrition, record-keeping, the manner of disciplining the children, the selection of foster homes, and other topics. One major adjustment resulting from the study came with the shift to a staff of trained social workers.
With its budget coming entirely from donations (and, starting in 1930, from the Richmond Community Fund), the Society struggled financially in its early years. By the early 1930's it was in danger of closing under the weight of $50,000 in debt. Led by then-Governor John Garland Pollard and other prominent supporters, the state-wide "Spring Emergency Campaign" of 1931 yielded enough funds to erase the Society's debt and bring a measure of financial stability. The Society later partnered with the United Way for several years as an additional source of funds.
The receiving home was closed in 1934, signaling the Society's move to an emphasis on temporary boarding home (foster) care in advance of permanent adoption placement. As the state became increasingly responsible for the protection of poor, abused, and neglected children, the Society found its niche in the placement of "children born out of wedlock of the higher middle classes, who...are not accepted by their families." Throughout the middle part of the century, the Society only took in infants under six months of age who were deemed "essentially normal," which included "the child with some physical problem who can nevertheless bring great happiness to his parents-by-adoption."
In the 1970's the Society began defining itself as an agency providing adoption services, pregnancy counseling, and foster care. It also started to accept children over the age of six months, and to place children of minority and mixed-race backgrounds. The 1980's and 1990's saw an increase in the Society's work with "hard to place" children, including babies with medical problems, older children, minority children, and sibling groups. This work led to the formation in 1998 of the Partnership for Adoptions (PFA) program. In a cooperative effort between the Children's Home Society, local departments of social services, and clinical professionals, PFA seeks to "train and prepare adoptive families to parent children with special needs." The success of the program has been honored by the National Association of Counties (2000) and with an Adoption Excellence Award (2003) from the United States Department of Health and Human Services.
While the Roanoke office and branches in other areas of the state have closed, the Children's Home Society of Virginia remains vital and forward-moving in its second century of service, with offices in Richmond and Fredericksburg. (Up-to-date as of 2010).
Scope and Content
Records, 1902-2008, of the Children's Home Society of Virginia include annual reports, board and committee files, clippings, financial and fundraising records, histories of the agency, manuals for CHS services, newsletters, photographs, and posters. This collection does not contain the children's case files.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. General Files
II. Board and Committee Files
III. Financial Records
IV. Fundraising
V. Photographs and Posters
VI. Clippings
Contents List
- Series I. General files, 1902-2008. (Box 1-8)
  General files include annual reports; issues of the quarterly newsletters Home Finder, 1920-1974 and 2000-2003, and Reaching Out to Virginia's Children, 1987-1999; Happy Endings, a promotional video about CHS, ca. 2000; publicity, invitations, photographs, and other items pertaining to events such as the Society's 100th anniversary celebration and various fundraisers; a 1964 radio program script; manuals on adoption and foster care (or "boarding") procedures; various overviews of the history, services, and structure of the Society; and limited correspondence, 1929-2006.
  - 30th anniversary celebration invitation, 30 January 1930. (Box 1)
  - 90th anniversary celebration, 1989. (Box 1)
  - 100th anniversary celebration, 2000. (Box 1)
  - A Child is Waiting (radio program script), 23-27 November 1964. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Adoption Operating Manual, Placement Division, ca. 1964-1967. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Annual reports, 1902-2007 (some gaps). (Box 2, Folder 3-15)
  - Annual reports, 1945-1963 (scrapbook). (Box 3)
  - Articles on adoption issues, ca. 1997-2005. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Caseworker's Manual, Preadoptive (Boarding) Division, 1959. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Charter and by-laws, updated to 1979. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - CHS: 1984-1985 (deconstructed binder). (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Photocopies of publicity, advertisements, etc., regarding the Children's Home society from 1984-1985.
  - CHS Christmas Cards, 1977 and undated. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - CHS general overview, ca. 1980. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Deconstructed binder with sections labeled "Charter and History," "Board of Directors Advisory Board and Staff," "Personnel Policies," "Program Services," "Financial," and "By-laws."
  - CHS general overview, 1990. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - CHS general overview, ca. 2008. (Box 4, Folder 8-10)
    Three copies with varying components of an informational packet including sections on CHS history, mission, board and staff, services, and revenue.
  - CHS Reports (newsletter), Spring 1980. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Come and See the Children's Home Society of Virginia (undated booklet). (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1929-2006. (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Correspondence numbers only six letters, and includes a Fredericksburg social worker's objection to the contents of two CHS mailings, 1974, and executive director Philip D. Holzman's response to a letter, 1982, questioning the organization's attempts to raise funds "for babies and small children you do not have."
  - Drawing (signed "Mays '67") of CHS building, Richmond. (Box 64)
  - Forms for adoption process, Va. Dept. of Social Services, 2000. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Happy Endings ca. 2000 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Promotional video about the Children's Home Society of Virginia. Includes testimonials from adoptive parents, adoptees, birth mothers, and CHS staff.
  - Historical Material (deconstructed binder). (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Various memos, late 1940's-early 1960's, on aspects of the CHS including the fee system, the Memorial Fund, intake policy, placement statistics, and organizational structure; staff meeting minutes from late 1946; and a short history of the Southwest Branch, 1947.
  - The History of the Children's Home Society of Virginia by Jacquelin Lee Warner, 1938. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Thesis for Master of Science in Social Work, College of William and Mary.
  - Home Finder (or The Virginia Children's Home Finder), 1920-1952. (Box 5, Folder 3-14)
    This quarterly newsletter typically included updates on the work of the Society, stories about children still in the care of the Society and ones who had already been adopted, fundraising appeals, thoughts on relevant topics in adoption, and essays on the value of adoption. Early issues feature many "before and after" studio portraits of children "as received" and after being taken into the care of the Society, along with notes on their progress.
  - Home Finder (or The Virginia Children's Home Finder), 1953-1974 and 2000-2003. (Box 6, Folder 1-10)
    This quarterly newsletter typically included updates on the work of the Society, stories about children still in the care of the Society and ones who had already been adopted, fundraising appeals, reports of events such as the Centennial Gala, thoughts on relevant topics in adoption, and essays on the value of adoption. The publication's name was changed from Home Finder at some point but restored in 2000. See also several issues, 1987-1999, of the re-named newsletter, Reaching Out to Virginia's Children.
  - Home Finder transcripts, ca. 1921-1967. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Indian tribes. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Literature for birth parents (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Literature re: adoption (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
  - Literature: CHS history, services (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
  - Literature re: special needs children (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - A Manual for Boarding Parents of the Children's Home Society of Virginia (Southwest Branch), April 1947 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Maybee, Mary McLeod (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous non-CHS brochures, literature (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Outreach and one-year plan, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Outreach packet materials, ca. 2006 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Parental Placement Adoption information packet, ca. 1997 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Personnel Practices Manual, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Policy statement, adult adoptee service, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Press releases, 1947 and undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Proceedings of the Conference on the Care of Dependent Children, 25-26 January 1909 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Reaching Out to Virginia's Children, 1987-1999 (Box 8, Folder 5-8)
    The quarterly newsletter of the Children's Home Society. The publication was originally named the Home Finder, but changed to Reaching Out to Virginia's Children for several years before resuming its former name in 2000. See also issues of the Home Finder, 1920-1974 and 2000-2003.
  - Response to inquiry re: CHS position on abortion, ca. 1982 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Service statistics, 2006-2007 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Speakers' kit (ca. 1970) (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - State Board of Social Services and other agency information (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Stout, Micki (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - United Way (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Volunteer handbook, ca. 2000 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - While You Wait... newsletter, April 1975 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Series II. Board and committee files, 1904-1987. (Box 9-18)
  Minutes and records from the governing Boards of the main office (Richmond), 1923-1987, and the Southwest Branch (Roanoke), 1904-1973. Board minutes touch on a range of topics, including property and financial matters, service statistics, personnel changes, fundraising, relevant legislation, community partnerships, and the relationship of the state office and the Roanoke branch. At times (particularly in earlier years), specific cases are discussed; as a result, access to many of these records is restricted. Please note that in some cases committee files were interfiled with the Board files. Therefore, it is best to check the records of each of the entities for a given time period in order to catch all relevant material. Other groups represented in this series include the Friends of the Children's Home Society and the Northern Virginia Advisory Committee.
  Arrangement: The series is arranged by office, with the Richmond files coming first (Boxes 9-16), followed by the Southwest Branch (Roanoke) files (Boxes 10-18). The Southwest Branch minutes are arranged in order of loose papers first, followed by volumes. There is some overlap between the two sets. There are occasional references to the work of the Southwest Branch in the Richmond office files and vice versa. Also, the records of a 1978 joint meeting between the two boards are filed towards the end of the Richmond section, in Box 16.
  Access Restriction
  Due to privacy concerns, portions of this Series are closed for a period of years, unless prior permission is obtained from the Children's Home Society of Virginia. See folder listings for more details.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1923-1939 (Box 9, Folder 1-10)
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1940-1959 (Box 10, Folder 1-8)
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1961-1967 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1969-1971 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors miscellaneous documents, 1969-1970, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors miscellaneous documents, 1980's (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Board of Sponsors, 1967-1973 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Board of Sponsors, 1963-1966 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Casework Committee, 1946-1958 (Box 11, Folder 6-9)
    These files contain sensitive information and are closed to the public until 2058. Permission to view before 2058 must be obtained in advance from the Children's Home Society of Virginia.
  - Casework Committee, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Executive Committee, 1944-1946 (Box 11, Folder 11-13)
  - Executive Committee, 1947-1967 (Box 12, Folder 1-10)
  - Executive Committee, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    These files contain sensitive information and are closed to the public until 2068. Permission to view before 2068 must be obtained in advance from the Children's Home Society of Virginia.
  - Executive Committee, 1969-1971 (Box 13, Folder 2-6)
  - Executive and Service Committee Minutes, 1980-May 1981 (deconstructed binder) (Box 13, Folder 7-8)
  - Executive and Service Committee Minutes, June 1981-1982 (deconstructed binder) (Box 13, Folder 9-10)
  - Executive Committee, 1985-1995 (Box 14, Folder 1-13)
  - Executive Committee, 1996-1997 (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
  - Finance Committee, 1929-1940 (Box 15, Folder 3-4)
  - Friends of the Children's Home Society, 1967-1974 (Box 15, Folder 5-6)
  - Friends of the Children's Home Society, 1983-1984 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Friends of the Children's Home Society minutes, 1967-1976 (Box 15, Folder 8-12)
  - Northern Virginia Advisory Committee, 1949-1957 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Northern Virginia Advisory Committee, 1958-1969 and undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Public Relations and Funding Committee, 1977-1980 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Semi-annual Joint Meeting, Board of Directors and Roanoke Advisory Board, 4 November 1978 (Box 16, Folder 3-4)
  - Service Committee Meeting Minutes, 1972-1997 (Box 16, Folder 5-12)
  - Southwest District Office, Advisory Board of the, by-laws, adopted and ratified, 1978 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Southwest Branch Board minutes, 1923-1925 (loose papers) (Box 17, Folder 2)
    These files contain sensitive information and are closed to the public until 2025. Permission to view before 2025 must be obtained in advance from the Children's Home Society of Virginia.
  - Southwest Branch Board minutes, 1928-1934 (loose papers) (Box 17, Folder 3)
    These files contain sensitive information and are closed to the public until 2034. Permission to view before 2034 must be obtained in advance from the Children's Home Society of Virginia.
  - Southwest Branch Board minutes, 1935-1936 (loose papers) (Box 17, Folder 4)
    These files contain sensitive information and are closed to the public until 2036. Permission to view before 2036 must be obtained in advance from the Children's Home Society of Virginia.
  - Southwest Branch Board minutes, 1937-1943 (loose papers) (Box 17, Folder 5-7)
  - Southwest Branch Board minutes, 1945-1973 (loose papers) (Box 17, Folder 8-14)
  - Southwest Branch Board minutes, 1904-1914 (volume) (Box 18)
    This item contains sensitive information and is closed to the public until 2014. Permission to view before 2014 must be obtained in advance from the Children's Home Society of Virginia.
  - Southwest Branch Board minutes, 1914-October 1923 (volume) (Box 18)
    This item contains sensitive information and is closed to the public until 2023. Permission to view before 2023 must be obtained in advance from the Children's Home Society of Virginia.
  - Southwest Branch Board minutes, November 1923-July 1926 (volume) (Box 18)
    This item contains sensitive information and is closed to the public until 2026. Permission to view before 2026 must be obtained in advance from the Children's Home Society of Virginia.
  - Southwest Branch Board minutes and financial statements, March 1928-June 1932 (volume) (Box 18)
    This item contains sensitive information and is closed to the public until 2032. Permission to view before 2032 must be obtained in advance from the Children's Home Society of Virginia.
- Series III. Financial records, 1927-2008. (Box 19-21)
  See also Series II for financial records that appear in Board and Finance Committee files.
  Arrangement: Volumes are filed at the end of the series.
  Due to privacy concerns, portions of this Series are closed for a period of years. Permission to view before end of closure period must be obtained in advance from the Children's Home Society of Virginia. See folder listings for more details.
  - Balance sheets, 1932-1942 (Box 19, Folder 1-2)
  - Balance sheets, 1947-1951 (Box 19, Folder 3-4)
  - Financial statements, years ended 30 June 2000 and 1999 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Memorial Fund performance summary, 30 October 2003 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Memorial Fund performance summary, 31 March 2008 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Building Fund cash book, 1967-1971 (Box 20)
  - Group home journal, 1976-1982 (volume) (Box 20)
  - Ledger and journal (Southwest Branch), 1932-1941 (volume) (Box 20)
  - Financial statements (Southwest Branch), 1927-1931 (volume) (Box 21)
    This item contains sensitive information and is closed to the public until 2031. Permission to view before 2031 must be obtained in advance from the Children's Home Society of Virginia.
- Series IV. Fundraising, 1921-2008. (Box 21-27)
  Files pertaining to the fundraising efforts of the Children's Home Society of Virginia, including mailings to donors, and records of gala events and golf tournaments. Please note that some files dealing with funding provided by the Old Dominion Foundation in the late 1950's contain potentially identifying information about children who were helped with the funds. As a result, these files are restricted.
  - Annual benefit, 2007, "Motown Get Down" (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Annual benefit, 2008, "Hooray for Hollywood" (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Appeal letters and mailings, 1950's-1960's (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Appeal letters and mailings, 1973-1975 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Appeal letters and mailings, 1977-1989 (Box 22, Folder 5-7)
  - Appeal letters and mailings, 1990-1999 (gaps) (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Appeal letters and mailings, 2005-2007 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Appeal letters and mailings, undated (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Breakfast of Champions posters, 1996-1999 (oversize) (Box 21)
  - Breakfast of Champions, 1996 (Box 22, Folder 11-12)
  - Breakfast of Champions, 1996 (Box 23, Folder 1-3)
  - Breakfast of Champions, 1997 (Box 23, Folder 4-8)
  - Breakfast of Champions, 1998 (Box 23, Folder 9-10)
  - Breakfast of Champions, 1999 (Box 24, Folder 1-4)
  - Building Fund, 1962-1969 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - CHS Phase II Report, Development Plan, Awareness Plan, ca. 1994 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - CHSVA Foundation, initial planning, 2004 (Box 24, Folder 7-8)
  - Foundations: 1973 annual report notices (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Foundations: 1973 replies (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Foundations: Armstrong Foundation (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Foundations, A-D (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Foundations, D (continued)-L (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Foundations, L (continued)-M (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Foundations, miscellaneous (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Foundations, N-O (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Foundations: Old Dominion Foundation, 1956-1959 (Box 25, Folder 6-7)
  - Foundations: Old Dominion Foundation, 1956-1959 (Box 25, Folder 8)
    This folder is closed to the public until 2059 due to privacy concerns. Permission to view before 2059 must be obtained in advance from the Children's Home Society of Virginia.
  - Foundations: Old Dominion Foundation, 1966-1968 (Box 25, Folder 9)
  - Foundations, P-R (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - Foundations, S-W (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Foundations, W (continued) (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Manual for Field Representative, ca. 1949 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Memorial fund donor book, 1921-1971 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Memorial gifts, 1968-1971 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous fundraising files, ca. 2003-2008 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - New building -- fundraising and dedication, 1967-1968 (Box 26, Folder 7)
  - State-Wide Finance Campaign, Children's Home Society of Virginia, May 1-15, 1933 (Box 26, Folder 8)
  - Summary of 1934 campaign (Box 26, Folder 9)
  - Wendy's Golf Classic, 1997 (Box 26, Folder 10-11)
  - Wendy's Golf Classics, 1998-1999 (Box 26, Folder 12)
  - Wendy's Golf Classics, 2000-2002 (Box 27, Folder 1-2)
  - Wendy's Golf Classics, 2003-2004, 2007 (Box 27, Folder 3)
- Series V. Photographs and posters, ca. 1903-ca. 2003. (Box 27-28 and two oversize folders (one in Oversize Box 64 and one in Oversize Cabinet 2, Drawer 12))